Guide to the Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
Lavoisier Manuscripts and Graphics Collection, circa 1750-1834 (bulk)
- Series I. Correspondence to or from Antoine Laurent Lavoisier
  - 1766-1786
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Baguelet, October 21, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Summary: Inquires whether her children have a share in the interests coming to her husband's family, and requests a loan for her son.
      Letter begins: "récves je vous prie Monsieur un million de / rémerciement…"
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Baguelet, October 25, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Summary: Dissatisfied with Lavoisier's reply, she restates her inquiry of October 21.
      Letter begins: "en remarquant dans votre lettre Monsieur / votre adeur a m'obligé.."
    - Baudon, Anne Margueritte Charlotte, comtesse de Ligniville (née comtesse de Ligniuille) [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, October 27, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 22 cm; holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Discusses legal procedures involved in the proposed transfer of money to her son.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur, l'objet de ma demande était le / désir..."
    - Duclombier, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, December 15, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Summary: Requests, on behalf of M. Chastenet, that Lavoisier send to M. Tocquiny a procuration for the money Lavoisier owes him.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / M. Chastenet qui arrive […] De la Campagne…"
  - 1786-1794
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] Mlle. Begon, Vendôme, January 11, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm;holograph signed.
      Summary: Sends 1,407 livres for salt storage at Vendôme.
      Letter begins: "Mademoiselle / Je vous demande bien pardon d'avoir tardé / aussi longtemps…"
    - Chastenet, ____, procureur au parlement. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Chastenet, September 10, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Summary: Pertains to the final steps of the business deal with M. Tocquiny and to legal matters concerning the ownership of Mlle. Punctis' house.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/ j'ai eu l'honneur d'aller chez vous ce matin…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, Paris, [to] Monsieur de Fougeroux, Paris, April 14, 1787 (Box 43, Folder 11)
      Physical Description: 2 p. on 1 leaf, 23 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Lavoisier informs Auguste Denis Fougeroux de Bondaroy, the director of the Académie des Sciences, that he has finished his Mémoire sur la nécessité de réformer et de perfectionner la nomenclature chimique.
      Letter begins: "J'ai reçu Monsieur mon cher confrère les deux lettres que vous m'avez fait l'honneur de m'écrire..."
    - Devernoy, [to] M. de Lavoisier, April 30, 1787 (Box 43, Folder 12)
      Physical Description: 3 p. on 1 leaf; 21 cm; letter autograph
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/J'ai l'honneur de vous remettre, avec les rapports, arrêtés, par votre dernier travail, celui de la saisie, faicte par les employés des entrées et ceux du département..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Comillas 1979
    - Le Coutelx de la Noraye, Madame. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, June 14, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 20a)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm;holograph signed. Accompanied by an attached draft letter from Lavoisier, date 14 June 1787.
      Summary: Seeks appointments of M. Du Vivier and his cousin M. Auboineau to the Régie des poudres. Note in Lavoisier's hand at top of letter: "Poudres et Salpetres R. le 23."
      Letter begins: "Je viens Monsieur réclamer vos bontés…"
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent [to] Mde. Le Coulteux de l'anoraye, Paris, June 24, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 20b)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 26 cm;holograph. Accompanied by an attached letter, dates 14 June 1787, from Madame Lecouteulx de La Noraye
      Summary: Draft answering her letter concerning the appointments of both Du Vivier and his cousin Auboineau, to the Régie des poudres.
      Letter begins: "Madame. / Il ne m'a pas été possible de / répondre plus tôt…"
    - Lavoisier, Antioine Laurent; le Faucheux, Desannois [to] Monseigneur le comte de Brienne, April 26, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 32 cm;Ms. signed.
      Summary: Requests that the road leading from La Rochelle to a neighboring saltpeter factory be preserved, and discusses administrative matters related to saltpeter. Marginal notes in different hand on p. [1].
      Letter begins: "Monseigneur. / Permettez nous de Vous rappeller la lettre..."
    - Hain de Villeneuve, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, April 30, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 24 cm;holograph signed. Seal attached.
      Summary: Proposes to make an appointment with Lavoisier, who is to pay what he owes Count d'Issoncourt. Draft of Lavoisier's response, dated 2 May, added on p. [1].
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / Je viens de recevoir une lettre et une procuration…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur de La Roche, June 22, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 22 cm; holograph.
      Summary: Draft asking M. de La Roche to inform Lavoisier when the inspector general plans to visit the Arsenal.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur le controlleur general doit…"
    - Tarbé, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, October 23, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Forwards a copy of instructions [Lavoisier MSS. 6.03a] sent to the provincial assemblies for the convocations of the departmental divisions.
      Letter begins: "J'ai l'honneur Monsieur de vous envoyer une copie du / Canevas d'Instruction…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to an unnamed uncle of M. Le Maître], Paris, November 1, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 18 cm;holograph signed.
      Summary: Lavoisier says he will support Le Maître's advancement in the Régie des poudres.
      Letter begins: "Je ne doute pas, Monsieur, qu'avec les / dispositions et la bonne volonté qu'apporte M. / Le Maître…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] M. de La Forte, La Rochelle, Paris, February 6, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 26 cm;Ms. signed. Also signed by Faucheux, Clouet and Desannois.
      Summary: They return a bill, unpaid for reasons explained.
      Letter begins: "Nous vous renvoyons, Monsieur, un effet de…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, ... [et al.] [to] M. de La Forte, La Rochelle, Paris, February 17, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 25 cm;Ms. signed. Also signed by Faucheux, Desannois, Clouet.
      Summary: Acknowledges earnings made at the Régie in January, and discusses the replacement of gunpowder which La Forte borrowed from the artillery.
      Letter begins: "Nous avons reçu, Monsieur, la lettre que vous / nous avez fait l'honneur de nous écrire le 3 de ce mois…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, ... [et al.] [to] M. de La Forte, La Rochelle, Paris, July 14, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 25 cm;Ms. signed. Also signed by Faucheux, Clouet and Desannois.
      Summary: Response to de La Forte's account of money earned by the Régie des poudres in June.
      Letter begins: "Nous avons reçu, Monsieur, la lettre que vous / nous avez fait l'honneur de nous écrire le 3…"
    - La Roche, ____, de. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, September 29, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 29a)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 20 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Forwards a letter of Mr. Janvin, and asks for consideration of Janvin's request that he receive a new comission for the sale of saltpeter. Note in Lavoisier's hand at top of p. [1]: "Poudres et Salpetres R. le 23 8bre. Negativement." Note and intials in third hand at top left corner of p. [1]. "J'ai l'honneur Monsieur, de vous / faire passer une lettre du Sr. Janvin /"
    - Janvin, ____, fils. [to an unnamed person], Melun, September 28, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 29b)
      Summary: As a saltpeter vendor at Melun, he requests that the commission of his father be transferred to his name.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / Connaissant toutes vos bontées pour moi / Je prends la liberté de vous interompre..."
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, ... [et al.] [to] M. de La Forte, La Rochelle, Paris, October 11, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Summary: They acknowledge de La Forte's account of July's shipment, and the earnings of the Régie des poudres in September.
      Letter begins: "Nous avons reçu, Monsieur, la lettre que / Vous nous avez fait l'honneur de nous é crire le / 2 de ce mois…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, ... [et al.] [to] M. de La Forte, La Rochelle, Paris, October 16, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 25 cm;Ms. signed. Also signed by Faucheux, Desannois, and Clouet.
      Summary: They acknowledge receipt of 3 "effets", and state that the potassium La Forte received should last 6 months. "Nous avons reçu, Monsieur, la lettre que vous nous/ avez fait l'honneur de nous écrire le 6 de ce mois /"
      Letter begins: "Nous avons reçu, Monsieur, la lettre que vous nous/ avez fait l'honneur de nous écrire le 6 de ce mois..."
    - Saussure, Horace Bénédict de, Genève, [to] Monsieur Lavoisier, February 11, 1790 (Box 43, Folder 13)
      Summary: Acknowledges receipt of Lavoisier's Taité élémentaire de chimie, and adopts Lavoisier's theories.
      Letter begins: "J'aurois du, Monsieur, vous accuser plus tôt la réception de votre ouvrage. Mays une maladie grave et très longue qu'a essuyée ma femme..."
      Bibliographic Reference: With an invoice 6.2.1970 (Charavay)
    - Black, Joseph [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Edinburgh, October 24, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Physical Description: 4 leaves; 27 cm;holograph signed (photograph) original in the Archives nationales.
      Summary: Black conveys the readiness with which the younger chemists adopt the new doctrine and the subsiding of his own aversion to the new nomenclature. "I am much obliged to you my dear sir for makeing me acquainted with your friend M. Terray…"
      Letter begins: "I am much obliged to you my dear sir for makeing me acquainted with your friend M. Terray…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v. 7, p. 9-11. French translation by Mme. Lavoisier in Annales de chimie, 1791, v. 8, p. 225
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur Parisis fils, Villers-Cotterêtes, Paris, November 9, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Summary: Discusses the management of Lavoisier's properties at Villers-Cotterêts.
      Letter begins: "Au moment ou M. Sivé notaire à / haute-fontaine, …"
    - Black, Joseph [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Edinburgh, December 28, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 27 cm;holograph signed (photograph) original in the Archives nationales.
      Summary: Grants consent for Lavoisier to publish his letter [Lavoisier MSS. 1.32], supporting the new system of chemistry.
      Letter begins: "Dear sir / Mr. Gahagan who is just returned to this place…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v. 7, p.12-13.
    - Kerr, Robert [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Edinburgh, January 21, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Physical Description: 3 leaves; 27 cm;holograph signed (photograph) original in the Archives nationales.
      Summary: Discusses the second edition of Kerr's translation of Lavoisier's Eléments de Chymie.
      Letter begins: "Sir / Soon after the publication of your Eléments de / Chymie I had the good fortune…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v.7, p. 13-14.
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur Parisis fils, Villers-Cotterêtes, Paris, July 22, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Summary: Discusses the management of Lavoisier's properties at Soisson, Crepy and surroundings. Note in different hand on p. [4].
      Letter begins: "Il y a apparence, Monsieur, et cher parent, que les/ obligations…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur Dupont / Lavoisier [and] Condorcet, Paris., July 28, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 26 cm;Ms. signed (photograph), original in the Eleutherian Mills Historical Library.
      Summary: Requests 500 copies of two letters by Milord Stanhope.
      Letter begins: "Les Commissaires de la Trésorerie Nationale…"
    - Wedgwood, Josiah [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Weymouth, August 7, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Summary: Agrees to carry out Lavoisier's wishes.
      Letter begins: "Sir! / Your obliging letter has found / me at this place…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v.7, p.14-15
    - Wedgwood, Josiah [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Etruria, August 18, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Summary: Sends details on refractory materials he has tested.
      Letter begins: "Sir! / On my return to my manufactory / here I made some essays…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v.7, p. 16-17, together with French translation.
    - Spallanzani, Lazzaro [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Pavia nel Milanese, September 1, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 40a)
      Physical Description: 4 leaves; 24 cm;holograph signed (photograph) original in the Archives nationales.
      Summary: Thanks Lavoisier for the Elémens de Chymie forwarded by Landriani, and speculates on the origin of air pockets found in lava flows.
      Letter begins: "Illmo. E Celebratissmo. Sigre. / Sono più di due mesi, che il Sigre. Cavalre. Landriani di Milano…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v.7, p.18-20
    - Spallanzani, Lazzaro [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Pavia nel Milanese, September 1, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 40b)
      Physical Description: 3 leaves, 24 cm;Ms. (photograph, transcript, handwritten).
      Summary: Thanks Lavoisier for the Elémens de Chymie forwarded by Landriani, and speculates on the origin of air pockets found in lava flows. "Très illustre et très célèbre Monsieur, / Il y a plus de deux mois que Mr. le Chavalier Landriani de Milan…"
      Letter begins: "Très illustre et très célèbre Monsieur, / Il y a plus de deux mois que Mr. le Chavalier Landriani de Milan… "
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v.7, p.20-21
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, ... [et al.] [to] Mss. Du Directoire du Département de Paris, October 27, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Summary: Informs them of sums made available to reimburse creditors of suppressed ecclesiastic establishments. "Nous avons l'honneur, Messieurs de vous prévenir que vous pouvez faire recevoir à / la Trésorie Nle. …"
      Letter begins: "Nous avons l'honneur, Messieurs de vous prévenir que vous pouvez faire recevoir à / la Trésorie Nle. … "
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] M. Isuardi, Arras, Paris, January 15, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 22 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Forwards two copies of his pamphlet "Sur la richesse territoriale de la France" (1791).
      Letter begins: "J'ai l'honneur, Monsieur, de vous adresser / deux exemplaires de la brochure…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, [to] [ Nicolas Charles Parisis ], March 28, 1792 (Box 43, Folder 14)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 23 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: About the purchase of lands located in Taillefontaine, purchased by Parisis for his cousin.
      Letter begins: "Je vous envoye cy inclus Monsieur et cher parent une reconnoissance de 3749 l. pour acquitter les 12 pour cent de l'acquisition des terres..."
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] M. Parisis fils, Vellers-Cotterêts, Paris, March 31, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Summary: Sends two certificates of residence to comply with requirement that absentee land-lords file certificates for each residence. "J'ai, Monsieur et Cher Parent, L'honneur de vous / envoyer deux certificats de résidence…"
      Letter begins: "J'ai, Monsieur et Cher Parent, L'honneur de vous / envoyer deux certificats de résidence…"
    - France. Régie des poudres et salpêtres, [letter signed by Antoine Laurent Lavoisier], [to] [one of the directors of the Ministère de la Guerre], April 25, 1792 (Box 43, Folder 15)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 20 cm
      Summary: About the new premises of the Régie des poudres et salpêtres.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/La Régie des Poudres vient d'être évincée d'un local qu'elle occupoit à La Rochelle et où elle avoit formé un établissement propre à la fabrication du salpêtre..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Scheler 3.1962
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to an unnamed man], Paris, May 29, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 23 cm;holograph signed.
      Summary: Discusses and recommends acceptance of proposals made by Borda to the Commission on Weights and Measures.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / J'ai L'honneur de vous transmettre copie d'une / Lettre de M. de Borda à M. Condorcet…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Louis XVI, June 1792 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 27 cm;holograph. Accompanied by a descriptive note allegedly by Leon de Chazelles ([1] p. on 2 leaves), and a photograph of the manuscripts ([4] pg. on 4 leaves).
      Summary: Draft of Lavoisier's refusal of the post of "Ministre des contributions publiques;" final version published in Grimaux, p. 215.
      Letter begins: "Sire/ Ce n'est ni par Crainte / pusillanime don’t je Suis incapable / ni par indifference pour la chose / publique…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent[to] M. Bonne Carerre, June 15, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 26 cm; holograph. Accompanied by photograph of manuscript ([2] p. on 2 leaves).
      Summary: Draft of letter which accompanied Lavoisier's letter to Louis XVI, recommending M. Caroillon de Vandeul and M. Dutramblay for the position of "ministre des contributions publiques."
      Letter begins: "J'ay bien honneur devoir faire…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent[to] M. Prieur, June 17, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 27 cm; holograph. Includes a draft of a separate letter to M. Arbogast (p. [1-3]).
      Summary: Draft of a note to accompany a copy of the letter sent to M. Arbogast (see p. [1-3]) and inviting Prieur to discuss the nomenclature on weights and measures.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur/ j'ay lhonneur de vous transmettre / copie de la lettre…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent[to] M. Arbogast, June 17, 1792 (Box 2, Folder ???)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 27 cm; holograph. Includes a draft of a separate letter to Prieur (p. [3] and [4]).
      Summary: Draft expressing interest in Arbogast's suggestions on the nomenclature for weights and measures and describing the nomenclature proposed by Prieur.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur / Nous nous sommes occupés hier / apres la séance de…"
    - Borda, Jean Charles de[to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, c. 1793 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 20 cm. holograph signed.
      Summary: Draft of a letter to be addressed to the "Commission des poids et mesures," concerning the funds necessary for the ongoing research. Note in Lavoisier's hand on top of p. [1]: "La Commission des poids et mesures au comite / d'instruction publique de la convention national / Citoyens representans" "L'assemblée nationale contituante a assigné un fond de /"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent[to] le ministre de l'intérieur, Paris, January 26, 1792 [1793] (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Physical Description: 1 leaf; 32 cm; manuscript signed.
      Summary: Informs the minister that the Académie only received part of the sum allotted for the year 1792 and requests payment of the balance.
      Letter begins: "Citoyen Ministre / Sur la somme de…"
    - Méchain, Pierre François André[to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Barcelone, May 11, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Physical Description: 3 leaves; 27 cm; manuscript signed (photograph), original in the Archives nationales.
      Summary: Informs Lavoisier of the various obstacles he has encountered on his geodetic mission in Spain.
      Letter begins: "Monsieur et cher confrere, / Les grandes difficultés que l'on éprouve depuis 3 semaines…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1949, v. 7, p. 28
    - Fourcroy, Antoine-François, Paris, [to] Citoyen Lavoisier, Paris, September 3, 1793 (Box 43, Folder 16)
      Physical Description: 1 p. on 1 leaf; 20 cm; autograph letter signed
      Summary: Asks Lavoisier a report about the Commission des poids et measures, to know its composition, its activities, its expenses.
      Letter begins: "Il est bien pressant, Citoyen, que vous m'adressiés le mémoire que vous a demandé dimanche le C. Romme, sur la Commission chargée des poids et mesures..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Scheler Nov. 1962
    - Bailliet, ____. [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, October 1, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 22 cm. holograph signed.
      Summary: The court clerk at the Section des piques thanks Lavoisier for his gift of sugar and 400 livres.
      Letter begins: "Le Secrétaire Greffier de la section des / Piques au citoyen Lavoisier. / Citoyen, / Vous trouverez ci joint…"
    - Delamare, ____.[to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, October 8, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 12 cm; holograph signed. Accompanied by a handmade folder with a note in the hand of Leon de Chazelles: "1793 / Billet de garde nationale / pour l'apothéose de marrat et de Lepelletier /"
      Summary: Invites Lavoisier to assist at the inauguration of Marat and Le Peletier.
      Letter begins: "Citoyent / Vous voudré bien vous Rendre…"
    - Cousin, Jacques Antoine Joseph [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Paris, November 30, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 25 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: Announces that the Bureau de consultation des arts et métiers rejects Lavoisier's resignation as president and assures Lavoisier that his patriotism throughout his career should free him of all worry. entendu la lecture de ta lettre..."
      Letter begins: "Citoyen / Le bureau de consultation des arts et metiers a…"
      Bibliographic Reference: Scheler, Lavoisier et le principe chimique, 1964, p. 127.
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Monsieur de Lavoisier, Port-Royal, December 1793 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Summary: Describes the living conditions in prison.
      Letter begins: "les prisonniers ma chere amie S'affectent / agreablement ou desagreablement des moindres / details…"
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Fourcroy, December 19, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Summary: Asks Fourcroy to arrange for his release in order to transfer the funds of the Académie des sciences; he also forwards a petition on behalf of the fermiers généraux.
      Letter begins: "Citoyen representant / Les circonstances ou je me trouve ne me permettent / pas desperer..."
      Bibliographic Reference: Royal Society, Notes and Records, 1958, v. 13, p. 59-60, and Scheler, Lavoisier et le principe chemique, 1964, p. 128
    - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent [to] Marie Anne Pierrette Lavoisier (Paulze), Port-Royal to Paris, December 19, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Physical Description: 2 leaves; 18 cm; holograph signed.
      Summary: From prison he expresses concern for his wife's welfare and seeks to reassure her about the future. "tu te donne ma chere bonne / amie bien de la peine, bien de / la fatigue de corps et desprit…"